A Guide to the Records of the Virginia War Office, 1781-1782.
Library of Virginia
Library of Virginia
Records of the Virginia War Offce,
1780-1782.
The Library of Virginia
54300
Virginia. War Office.
11 volumes.
Administrative Information
Arranged alphabetically.
Access Restrictions
Use microfilm when available.
Acquisition Information
Acquired prior to 1905.
Historical Information
When it abolished the Board of War in 1780, the General Assembly established the position of Commissioner of the War Office at its May 1780 session to replace it. The position was to be appointed by the governor, with advice of council (Chapter XXIV). The War Office was created to oversee recruits' vouchers, officers' commissions, returns from county lieutenants, military claims to land warrants, and pension certificates during the Revolutionary War.
A year later the powers of the Commissioner were extended (Chapter XV, May 1781).
The office was abolished in Oct 1782 in an attempt at economy at the close of hostilities and the duties appertaining thereto were transferred to the executive or his designee (Chapter XIV).
Colonel George Muter, the first commissioner, resigned his position on March 22, 1781, and was replaced by Colonel William Davies.
Scope and Content
Virginia War Office Records include Account book, 1781; Journal, 1781; Minute book, 1781-1782; Letterbooks, 1780-1782; Index to letterbooks, 1781-1782. There are non-related in this collection (described below) that fall outside of these dates.
For additional records see the Governor's Executive Papers for this time period.
See also Miscellaneous Reel 4266, Correspondence of William Davies, Commissioner of the War Office, 1780-1782. Includes incoming correspondence and is part of the Robert Alonzo Brock Collection.
Contents List
- Account book, Letterbook, and Pension Register, 1781-1801., Extent: 1 v.
  This bound volume contains three unrelated items.
  Accounts of the War Office, 1781 Jan-Oct, is a record of warrants issued in the War Office and includes for certificates for bounty, pay, purchase of arms, foundry, and construction, among others. The volume is arranged haphazardly by the name of the person to whom the warrant was issued and entries include date, reason for the warrant, and the amount. The credit side of the ledger is consistently empty.
  Letterbook, 1789 Oct-1792 Jan, includes correspondence and militia reports of Samuel Coleman, Assistant Clerk for the Council of State.
  Pension Register, 1786-1801, is a list of certificates issued for pensions. Entries include name, rank, corps, residence, when pensioned and allowance. Includes the name of many widows and orphans.
  Previously known as WAR 29 in the Calendar of Transcripts.
  Also available on Miscellaneous Reel 633 (identified as Register).
- Journal, 1781 January 18-December 31., Extent: 1 v. (314 p.)
  This journal provides a daily recording of activities including letters sent, warrants, and orders issued, all connected with the business of providing goods and services in support of the military. On occasion, the answer to a specific inquiry is entered below it.
  This volume is arranged chronologically and there is no index.
  Previously known as WAR 53 in the Calendar of Transcripts.
  Also available on Miscellaneous Reel 633 and 990.
- Minute book, 1781 November 2-1782 January 1., Extent: 1 v. (34 p.)
  This Minute book provides a record of business conducted by the War Office in regards to letters sent, orders and warrants issued, and certificates granted. Entries for Nov 18, 1781, have been crossed through.
- Letterbooks, 1780 July 21-1982 Dec 2., Extent: 8 v.
  Letterbooks include copies of the outgoing correspondence of the War Office. While there are no gaps, there is some overlapping of dates in the volumes. All volumes except for Letterbook, 1780 July 21-1781 Jan 2, are indexed. The separate index volume indexes WAR volumes 55-59 (designating them with letters B, C, F, E, and G respectively).
  Letterbook, 1781-1786, includes War Office, 1781 Dec 24-1782 Dec 2; and Council of State, 1782 Dec 24-1786 July 12.
  Also available on Miscellaneous Reels 632-633, and 990-992.
  - Letterbook (no index), 1780 July 21-1781 Jan 2. (Volume 1)
  - Letterbook (WAR 54), 1781 Jan 18-Sept 1. (Volume 2)
  - Letterbook (WAR 55, B), 1781 Aug 15-Nov 1. (Volume 3)
  - Letterbook (WAR 56, C), 1781 Nov 2-1782 Jan 22. (Volume 4)
  - Letterbook (WAR 59, F) - War Office and Council of State Journal, 1781 Dec 24-1782 Dec 2; 1782 Dec 24-1786 July 12. (Volume 5)
  - Letterbook (WAR 58, E), 1782 Jan 22-May 5. (Volume 6)
  - Letterbook (WAR 57, G), 1782 May 6-Oct 12. (Volume 7)
  - Index, 1781 Aug 15-1786 July 12. (Volume 8)